Finding Aid for the Louisa F. France Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Louisa F. France Collection
1920s-1970s
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0152
4.2 linear_feet
The Louisa F. France Collection documents over six decades of musical performances staged in the United States and Europe. Measuring 4.2 linear feet, the collection is organized chronologically and represents a wide spectrum of classical performers and musical styles. The earliest programs date back to 1920s performances by Sergey Rachmanioff (1873-1943) and Jascha Heifetz (1901-87) at the Lyric Theatre in Baltimore, Maryland. Other key performance venues in the United States represented in the collection include the Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center and Carnegie Hall in New York City as well as the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington, D.C.
Of special interest to researchers are the pre-World War II programs from Vienna and Salzburg, Austria; Munich, Dresden and Bayreuth, Germany; and Paris, France in the months leading up to the Nazi occupation. There are also several post-war items from London, England; Cremona, Italy; Brussels, Belgium; Innsbrook, Austria; Gottingen and Nurnberg, Germany.
In the late 1940s, Ms. France moved to Nashville with her husband, Dr. Richard France (Vanderbilt University Medical School Faculty 1948-85), where she and Dr. France patronized the local performance art scene. Items representing music programs staged at various churches in Nashville as well as those presented by George Peabody College for Teachers, Fisk University, Blair School of Music and the Nashville Symphony all are included in this collection.
Also included in the collection is small cache of booklets on English and European luthiers, composers and historic sites as well as souvenir programs for the Vienna Boys Choir, Leopold Stokowski and the All-American youth Orchestra, and Robert Shaw’s Choral Ensemble. The items contained herein complement a collection of commemorative coins from Austria. Minted from 1929 – 1937, the series honors composers and artists including Franz Schubert, Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart and Franz Joseph Hayden. Although some items are seventy years old, the overall condition of the materials in the collection is stable and good.
- 1922 – May 1930
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 1)
    Boston Symphony Orchestra
    Feodor Chaliapin
    The Chicago Opera
    Giuseppe DeLuca
    Amelita Galli-Curci
    The German Grand Opera Company [Baltimore, MD]
    Harrisburg [PA] Symphony Orchestra
    Jascha Heifetz
    Vladimir Horowitz
    The Johns Hopkins Orchestra
    Juilliard String Quartet
    La Argentina
    Hans Kindler
    Paul Kochanski
    Fritz Kreisler
    Kreutzbert & Georgi
    London String Quartet
    Giovanni Martinelli
    Yehudi Menuhin
    Metropolitan Opera [NY]
    Grace Moore
    Mozart Festival [Harrisburg, PA]
    New York Philharmonic (Arturo Toscanini conducting)
    Ignace Jan Paderewski
    The Philadelphia Orchestra
    Rosa Ponselle
    Peabody Conservatory of Music [Baltimore, MD]
    Shanghai Municipal Orchestra
    Sergey Rachmaninoff
    Alberto Salvi
    Mme. Schumann-Heink
    John Philip Sousa
    Lawrence Tibbett
    and others
- June 1930 – 1935
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 2)
    Bach Festival [Bethlehem, PA]
    Baltimore Symphony Orchestra (with George Siemonn conducting)
    Boston Symphony Orchestra (directed by Dr. Serge Koussevitzky)
    Budapest String Quartet
    Shura Cherkassky [Constitution Hall, Washington, DC]
    Claire Clairbert
    Compinsky Trio
    Don Cossack Chorus
    D’oyly Carte Opera Company
    German Grand Opera Company
    Mercersburg Academy [PA] Carillon Group
    Metropolitan Opera Company [NY]
    Monte Carlo Ballet Russe
    Musical Arts Quartet
    National Symphony Orchestra (conducted by Hans Kindler)
    New York Philharmonic [Arturo Toscanini with guest
    conductor Sir Thomas Beecham]
    Paderewski
    Philadelphia [PA] Orchestra (conducted by Leopold Stokowski with guest appearance by Vladimir Horowitz)
    Ruggiero Ricci
    Roth Quartet
    Carlos Salzedo
    San Carlo Grand Opera
    Ted Shawn and his Ensemble of Men Dancers
    Igor Stravinsky and Samuel Dushkin
    Joseph Szigeti
- 1936 – 1937
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 3)
    Ballet Russe of Monte Carlo
    Baltimore String Symphony
    Baltimore Symphony Orchestra (including Concert for Young People)
    Paul Bernard and Gardner Jencks
    Shura Cherkassky
    Coolidge Quartet
    Curtis String Quartet
    Library of Congress Festival of Chamber Music
    Tribute Concert to Charles Martin Loeffler (presented by the Library of Congress, Washington, DC)
    Marcel Maas
    Metropolitan Opera Company Musical Arts Quartet
    National Symphony
    Pro Arte String Quartet
    Savoy Company
    Trio Italiano
    Also included in this box are souvenir postcards and brochures from Cremona, Italy; bicentennial commemorative brochures on Antonio Stradivari; Opern Theatre, Konzerthaus-Quartett, Musica Viva Orchester, Weissgarber Quartet, Marian Anderson, Emil von Sauer, Helen Teschner Tas, Rose-Quartett; Germany.
- 1938 – 1940
  - Programs include performances at venues in Europe including: (Box 4)
    Opern Theater [Berlin]
    Gefellfchaft der Musikfreunde [Vienna]
    Burg Theater [Germany]
    Budapest [Hungary]
    Prague [Czechoslovakia]
    Paris [France]
    Academie Nationale de Musique et de Danse
    Theatre National De L’Opera Comique
    Festival [Igor] Stravinsky, [Paris]
    Salzburg [Austria] Festspiele
    Dresden [Germany] Opernhaus
    Festival Bayreuth [Munich]
    Orchestre de la Societe Philharmonique de Paris
    [Hector] Berlioz
    14th Haslemere Festival of Ancient Music [Surrey, England]
    Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo with the London Symphony Orchestra and the London Philharmonic Orchestra, Royal Opera House [London]
    Pamphlet: The Work and Ideas of Arnold Dolmetsch - Dolmetsch and his Instruments
  - U.S. programs include performances by and/or at the following venues
    All-American Youth Orchestra (conducted by Leopold Stokowski)
    Baltimore Civic Opera Company
    Belgian Piano String Quartet
    Berkshire Symphony Festival, Tanglewood, MA (includes special Allied Relief Fund Benefit for British Aid)
    Virgil Fox
    Kolisch Quartet
    Library of Congress Ninth Festival of Chamber Music
    Metropolitan Opera Company, New York
    The National Symphony Orchestra at Baltimore
    New Jersey Symphony Orchestra
    Philharmonic Symphony Society of New York
    The Town Hall, New York (cover features a photo of the Trapp Family Choir)
- 1941 – 1951
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 5)
    The American Ballad Singers
    The Bach Choir
    Bethlehem, [PA] Bach Festival
    Ballet Russe
    Baltimore Symphony Orchestra
    Bela Bartok and Ditta Pasztory (Mrs. Bela Bartok)
    Bennington [VT] Festival
    Berkshire Symphonic Festival [Tanglewood, MA]
    Carnegie Hall Golden Anniversary commemorative program
    Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra
    Paul Drape and Larry Adler, Ryman Auditorium, Nashville, TN
    Ecole Francaise de Middlebury
    Fisk Jubilee Singers
    Virgil Fox (sponsored by the Fisk University Concert Series)
    Joseph Fuchs
    George Peabody College for Teachers Concert Series (separately and with the University of the South)
    Homewood Quartet
    Indianapolis Symphony Orchestra (Fabien Sevitzky, conductor)
    Kolisch String Quartet
    Kungsholm Miniature Grand Opera Theatre of Chicago commemorative program
    La Scala Opera Company
    Robert McDowell
    The Nashville Symphony (William Strickland, conductor)
    National Symphony Orchestra (Hans Kindler, Conductor), Washington, DC
    Orchestra of the New Friends of Music (conducted by Fritz Stiedry)
    Roth Quartet [Brigham Young University, Salt Lake City, Utah]
    Saint Louis Sinfonietta
    The Town Hall [NYC]
    Ward-Belmont Conservatory of Music
    Leonard Warren
    Yale Glee Club
    Vermont Sesquicentennial Program, 1941
- 1952 – 1964
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 6)
    Ballet Theatre Foundation
    Beaux Arts Trio of New York
    Mary Louise Boehm
    Brevard [PA] Music Center
    The Cathedral Singers
    Chicago Symphony String Quartet
    Chicago Symphony Orchestra (Louis Lane, Guest Conductor)
    Gregory Colson
    Danish National Orchestra
    Festival Quartet
    Don Cossack Chorus and Dancers
    Clifford Curzon
    Ernst Von Dohnanyi
    First Presbyterian Carillon Dedication Concert (Nashville, TN)
    The Fisk Jubilee Singers
    The Fisk University Choir
    Fisk University 25th, 27th and 34th Annual Festival of Music and Art
    Nicola Gedda
    Johana Harris
    Kees Kooper
    Josef Marais and Miranda
    Nashville Symphony Orchestra (with Guy Taylor conducting)
    Nashville Symphony String Quartet
    New Music String Quartet
    New York String Sextet
    Peabody Demonstration School Recital Series
    Philadelphia [PA] Orchestra
    Pittsburgh [PA] Symphony Orchestra
    Michael Rabin
    Luisa Ribacchi and Guido Cantelli at Carnegie Hall (NYC)
    Rise Stevens
    Helen Traubel
    Robert Shaw Chorale and Orchestra
    St. Louis Municipal Opera
    United States Air Force Band
    University of the South Choir
    Vienna Boys Choir
    Walden String Quartet
    Bruno Walter at Carnegie Hall (NYC)
  - Playbills, publications and miscellaneous items include:
    “Singin’ Billy,” 1952 and 1955 productions by Peabody College and Vanderbilt Music Dept.
    “St. Louis Woman,” “Cosi Fan Tutte” and “Member of the Wedding,” presented by the Circle Players
    “Sunny Side Up” presented by the Princeton Triangle Club
    “Bartleby,” presented by the Oberlin [OH] College Conservatory of Music
    Poetry reading of works by R. P. Warren, M. Moore, A. Tate, D. Davidson, J. C. Ransom
    Bravo Magazine (Vol I, No. 2; Vol. II, No. 1; Vol. II, No. 3) 95th Annual Convention for Tennessee Education Association
- 1965 – 1969
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 7)
    Baltimore Symphony Orchestra (Brian Priestman, and Leopold Stokowski, Conductors)
    Beaux Arts String Quartet
    Berliner Camerata Musicale
    Boston Symphony Orchestra [Berkshire Festival at Tanglewood, MA]
    Cadet Glee Club (Virginia Military Institute at Hollins College and Robert E. Lee Memorial Episcopal Church)
    Chamber Symphony of Philadelphia
    Christ Church Parish (Nashville)
    Eastman Quartet
    George Goodman (at Fisk University)
    Guarneri String Quartet
    Hampden-Sydney College Glee Club
    Hollins College Student Recital and “A Program of Theatre Dance” (1967 and 1968)
    Hungarian Quartet
    Julliard String Quartet
    Le Danseurs Africains (first U. S. performance)
    Lenox String Quartet
    Lucktenberg Duo
    The Little Symphony of Nashville presents “An Evening of the Avant-Garde Arts”
    Nashville String Quartet
    Nashville Symphony Orchestra (Willis Page, conductor; Thor Johnson, Music Director and Conductor)
    Nashville Youth Symphony
    New York Philharmonic (with Andre Kostelanetz conducting)
    New York Woodwind Quintet
    George Peabody College School of Music Recital Series
    George Peabody College for Teachers Recital Series
    Philadelphia Orchestra
    The Romeros
    St. George’s Episcopal Church Fourth Sunday Music Series
    St. Louis Orchestra
    Grete Sultan and Barbara Wieman (Town Hall, NYC)
    Charles Treger (Carnegie Hall, NYC)
    University of North Carolina Choir
    Vanderbilt University Center Choral Union and Center Orchestra
    Washington Square Chorus and Orchestra (NYU)
  - Playbills, publications and miscellaneous items include (Box 7)
    “An Evening of One-Act Plays” by Tennessee Williams and Samuel Beckett presented by Vanderbilt University Theatre
    “Kaleidoscope ’67” presented by the Circle Players
    “The Threepenny Opera” presented by Peabody School of Music
    Nashville Symphony Newsletter, Vol. XIII, No. 5; March 1968
    Program for the 93rd Commencement Exercises of Meharry Medical College 23rd Composers’ Conference and Chamber Music Center at Bennington College [VT]
    Guide for Cheekwood’s Christmas “Trees of Many Lands” exhibit
    Hollins College Parents’ Day [Roanoke, VA] Materials
    Peabody College School of Music Seminar in Piano Teaching schedule and program
    Signe Quale (Memphis State University, University of the South and First Unitarian Church, Nashville)
- 1970 – 1975
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 8)
    Avante Garde III
    Bamberg Symphony Orchestra
    Blair Academy of Music Student Recital Series
    Blair String Quartet
    Candler Choraliers
    Cheekwood Chamber Music Series
    Christ Church Parish Concert Series (Nashville)
    Van Cliburn
    Collegiate Chorale
    Catherine Crozier
    Dvorak String Quartet
    Eastman Brass Quintet
    First Presbyterian Church
    George Peabody College School of Music Series (various student performers)
    I Solisti Veneti
    Joint University Choir (GPC)
    Mark Kaplan and Samuel Sanders
    King College Symphonic Choir
    The King’s Singers
    Kurrende Student Choir of Berlin (US tour 1972)
    London Symphony Orchestra (at Carnegie Hall with Andre Previn conducting)
    Marlboro Trio
    Morehouse College Glee Club
    Nashville Baroque and Classical Society Concert Series
    Nashville Chamber Brass Society
    Nashville Chamber Singers
    Nashville Symphony Orchestra
    Nashville University Center Council
    New London Ballet with Guest Artist [Dame] Margot Fonteyn
    New York Philharmonic (Lincoln Center)
    Jean-Pierre Rampal and Robert Veyron-Lacroix
    Scarritt College Chapel Choir and the Scarritt Singers
    St. Paul’s Evangelical Lutheran Church
    Trombone Ensemble of the University of Oklahoma
    University of Louisville Brass Quintet
    Warsaw String Quartet
  - Playbills, publications and miscellaneous items include (Box 8)
    “Die Fledermaus” performed by the Turnau Opera Players
    “Der Freischutz” presented by The Hartford [MD] Opera Theatre
    “H.M.S. Pinafore” presented by the Theatre Nashville Playhouse
    “Everyman” performed by Anthony Quayle and the Clarence Brown Scholar’s Troupe
    World of Gilbert & Sullivan presented by [Nashville] Community Concert Association
    Tribute Concert & Memorial Dinner in Recognition of John Wesley Work, III sponsored by Nashville Chapter of Links
    Seminar in Piano Teaching (GPC)
  - Programs and other materials from European venues (Box 8)
    Der Widerspenstigen Zahmung Ballet nach Shakespeare von John Cranko
    “Carmen” at the Staatsoper
    “Cinderella” at Komische Oper, Berlin
    “Die Liebe Zu Zrei Orangen” at Komische Oper, Berlin
    “Hansel und Gretel,” Deutsche Staatsoper Berlin
    “Tosca” at the Staatsoper
    Berliner Barock Orchester
    Deutsche Oper Berlin
    James Galway, Amerika Haus Berlin
    Igor Kipnis, Amerika Haus Berlin
    Salzburg Mozart Festival (includes performances of “Don Giovanni,” “Die Zauberflote,” “Macbeth”)
    Symphonisches Orchester Berlin
    Opern Journal, Nos. 2, 3, and 4 Oct., Nov. & Dec. 1970
- 1976 – 1985
  - Programs include performances by and/or at the following venues (Box 9)
    American String Quartet
    Annapolis Brass Quintet
    Arioso Woodwind Quintet
    Bach Aria Group (Fisk University Concert Series)
    Blair Academy of Music
    Blair Chamber Players
    The Centennial Club
    Christ Church Parish
    Christ Episcopal Church
    Fu Shing Chinese Opera Troupe (American Tour)
    The Gurdjieff Movements
    Illinois Kabuki Theatre with Shozo Sato
    Kentucky Wesleyan Singers
    The Mozarteum Quartet Salzburg, Tennessee Performing Arts Center, Nashville
    Nashville Baroque and Classical Society Series
    Nashville Symphony Orchestra (John Nelson, Music Advisor and Michael Charry Music Director and Conductor)
    Jessye Norman with the New York Philharmonic, Lincoln Center
    Pablo Casals Trio
    Peabody Chamber Trio
    The National Symphony Orchestra at Kennedy Center, Washington, DC
    New Hampshire Music Festival (w/ Thomas Nee conducting)
    New York Philharmonic at Lincoln Center
    Oberlin Baroque Ensemble
    The Pennsylvania Ballet
    The Piedmont Chamber Orchestra
    The Philadelphia Orchestra at Jackson Hall, Tennessee Performing Arts Center, Nashville
    Marek Piskunov and Alexander Piskunov
    Zina Schiff (Fisk University Concert Series)
    Peter Serkin
    Robert Stallman and Edwin Swanborn
    Isaac Stern with the Nashville Symphony Orchestra
    Summermusik at Cheekwood
    Christian Teal and Enid Katahn
    Tel Aviv String Quartet
    Tokyo String Quartet (Sarratt)
    Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra at Carnegie Hall (with Leonard Bernstein conducting)
    The Vienna Quintet
    Ragin Wenk and Kaare Ornung
    Westminster (PA) College Choir
  - Playbills, publications and miscellaneous items include (Box 9)
    Façade an entertainment with poems by Edith Sitwell & Music by William Walton
    George Peabody College Seminar in Piano Teaching Recital Series
    Premiere Magazine, Fall 1980, Winter 1980-81 (with NSO series programs)
    Metropolitan Opera National Council Mid-South Auditions
    “Washington Square” presented by the Augusta Opera Company
  - International Concerts (Box 9)
    Familiengottesdienst zum Sommerfest 1977 (Gottingen), Nurnberg, Innsbruck
    “Simon Boccanegra” at the Opera National/Theatre Royal de la Monnaie (Directeur Maurice Huisman)
    Societe Philharmonique de Bruxelles (Filharmonische Vereniging van Brussel)
- 1934 – 1985
  - Souvenir programs and other materials: (Box 10)
    25th Anniversary Booklet [1935] on Neues Wiener Konservatorium
    Biography of Paganiniana, published by the Library of Congress, 1945 Reprint of Show Magazine, March 1964
    Tour Program for All American Youth Orchestra (dir. by Leopold Stokowski), 1940
    60th Anniversary Commemorative program for the Boston Symphony, 1941
    Robert Shaw Choral and String Ensemble Tour Program, c. 1952
    NDR Symphony Orchestra of Hamburg, 1962-63 tour program
    Vienna Choir Boys tour program, c. early 1960s
    A Tanglewood Dream, 25th Anniversary Album, The Berkshire Music Center, 1965
    Booklet for Geigenbaumuseum Mittenwald-Bayern, date unknown
    Biography of Matthias Klotz von Mittenwald by Dr. Adolf Layer, 1970
    Schones Mittenwald tour booklet, likely 1970
    Brochure on the Pilcher Organ housed at the Cathedral of the Incarnation, Nashville, TN, date unknown
    The Claymont School for Continuous Education course catalog for AY 1979-80
    Claymont Communications Wholesale Book Catalog, 1979
    Duetscher Festspiesommer program, 1939 [oversized storage]